Guide to the Larry LeSueur papers, 1935-2003 MS2307
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Larry LeSueur papers
1935-2003
1940-1984
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lesueur, Laurence Edward
Lesueur, Amy
MS2307
10 Linear Feet 17 document boxes, 3 flat boxes, and 1 film
Laurence Edward "Larry" LeSueur was a Peabody-award winning radio correspondent best known as one of "Murrow's Boys," a band of international correspondents assembled in Europe before and during World War II by Edward R. Murrow for CBS. On D-Day, June 6, 1944, LeSueur was one of the first journalists to land at Normandy and report back news of the battle to Americans at home. This collection contains typewritten scripts, correspondence, articles, journals, audiocassettes and audio reels, and artifacts documenting LeSueur's 40-year career as a radio correspondent. Radio scripts and newspaper clippings include LeSueur's vivid accounts of war, written while he was stationed abroad from 1939 through the end of World War II. Other scripts, delivered while LeSueur was a White House correspondent, feature his first-person descriptions of business at the highest levels of government. The material dates from 1935 to 2003.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains typewritten scripts, correspondence, articles, journals, audiocassettes and audio reels, and artifacts documenting LeSueur's 40-year careeer as a radio correspondent. Radio scripts and newspaper clippings include LeSueur's vivid accounts of war, written while he was stationed abroad from 1939 through the end of World War II. Other scripts, delivered while LeSueur was a White House correspondent, feature his first-person descriptions of business at the highest levels of government. In addition, audiocassettes and audio reels include some of LeSueur's broadcasts, as well as oral histories, interviews, and memories of D-Day. The material dates from 1935 to 2003.
Biographical / Historical
Laurence Edward "Larry" LeSueur was a Peabody-award winning radio correspondent best known as one of "Murrow's Boys," a band of international correspondents assembled in Europe before and during World War II by Edward R. Murrow. He was born in New York in 1909, and began his career as a print journalist for United Press in the 1930s. He left New York for London in 1939, introduced himself to Murrow, and secured a position with him on the CBS Radio Network. He reported from the Russian front in 1941 and 1942, with a weekly radio broadcast called "An American in Russia," and wrote a book on the experience called Twelve Months that Changed the World, published in 1943.
On D-Day, June 6, 1944, LeSueur was one of the first journalists to land at Normandy and report back news of the battle to Americans at home. He covered Europe throughout the war, including broadcasting news of the liberation of Paris. After the war, LeSueur continued broadcasting for CBS Radio as White House correspondent, most notably from the Paris Peace Conference. He left CBS in 1963 but continued covering the White House, for Voice of America, until his retirement in 1984. He died on February 5, 2003 at the age of 93.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Amy LeSueur, 2012 (2012.059).
Arrangement
Organized into six series: Radio scripts, Subject files, Notebooks and journals, Audiovisual, Artifacts, and Clippings.
Radio broadcasting -- United States; World War, 1939-1945; War correspondents; Murrow, Edward R. -- Archives; Lesueur, Amy
- Radio scripts, 1942-1981; series 1; 4.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains typed scripts prepared by LeSueur for radio broadcasts, first for CBS News and then for Voice of America. Many include handwritten edits. Topics of interest include: wartime Russia, the Battle of Normandy, wartime London, the Paris Peace Conference, and the administrations of American presidents Kennedy, Johnson, Nixon, Ford, Carter, and Reagan. They date from 1942 to 1981.
  - Draft scripts, 1942; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1943; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts [1 of 2], 1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts [2 of 2], 1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts [1 of 2], 1945; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft scripts [2 of 2], 1945; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Draft Scripts, 1941-1945; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Draft Scripts (originals - fragile), 1942-1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Draft scripts, 1963 January-July; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1963 August-November; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts, 1964 July-1965 April; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts, 1965 May-August; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts, 1966 February-May; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1966 June-September; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts, 1966 October-1967 May; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts, 1967 May-July; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts, 1967 August-November; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1967 December; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts, 1968 January-May; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts, 1968 June-August; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts, 1968 September-December; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1969 January-March; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts, 1969 March-October; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts, 1969 October-November; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts, 1969 December; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Draft scripts, 1970 January-February; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Draft scripts, 1970 March-May; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Draft scripts, 1970 June-August; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1970 September-December; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts, 1971 May-August; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts, 1973 April-June; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts, 1974 January-February; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Draft scripts, 1974 March-April; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Draft scripts, 1974 May-July; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1974 August-December; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts, 1975 April-July; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts, 1975 September-December; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts, 1976 January-April; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Draft scripts, 1976 May-1977 January; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Draft scripts, 1977 March-December; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Draft scripts, 1978; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Draft scripts, 1979; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Draft scripts, 1980; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Draft scripts, 1981; Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Subject files, 1944-2003; Series 2; 1 Linear Feet
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains collected articles, written histories, correspondence, and biographical information. Major topics of interest include Edward R. Murrow, the invasion of Normandy on D-Day, and the Paris Peace Conference of 1946. Material dates from 1944 to 2003.
  - American Society of the French Legion of Honor, undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - CBS correspondence, 1949-1964; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - CBS Radio, 1944; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Central America, 1968; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1944-2003; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1944; Series 2 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Cronkite/Johnson interview, 1969; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - D-Day commemorations and memories, 1984; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Le Sueur biographical information, 1968; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Memories of Your Father" [Edward R. Murrow] by Chester S. Williams, Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Mexico, 1967; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Murrow obituaries, 1965; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - New York University, 1966; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Paris Conference [1 of 2], 1946; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Paris Conference [2 of 2], 1946; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Remembrances from D-Day, undated; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Script for a play, undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "The Soviet Army" by Larry Le Sueur, undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Trip to Asia with President Johnson, 1966; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Unforgettable Edward R. Murrow," Readers Digest, 1968-1969; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Voice of America history, undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Notebooks and journals, 1941-1985; Series 3; 1.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains notebooks, journals, appointment books, passports, press passes, and licenses used by LeSueur from 1941 to 1985 while a radio correspondent.
  - Notebooks and journals, 1941-1955; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks and journals, 1941-1955; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks and journals, 1941-1955; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Appointment books, 1960-1969; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Appointment books, 1970-1985; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Budget notebooks, undated; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks, undated; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Passports, press passes, and licenses, 1942-1984; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Audiovisual, 1935-1993; Series 4; 1 Linear Feet
  All cassettes are contained in one box without arrangement.
  This series contains audiocassettes and audio reels of LeSueur including news broadcasts, interviews, and oral histories. The material dates from 1935 to 1993. Some cassettes are copies of early broadcasts originally recorded on other audio formats.
  - Edward R. Murrow Selections, Newsroom, Larry LeSueur, undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 1)
  - Larry LeSueur on NPR, subject: D-Day, undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 2)
  - 5 Correspondent Reports from Larry LeSueur, undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 3)
  - D-Day Despatches: Broadcasts and reports from BBC War Correspondents involved in the Normandy Invasion of June 1944, undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 4)
  - The Murrow Boys, C. Roberts, 1996 June 11; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 5)
  - CBS News, 1935-1945; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 6)
  - LeSueuer, 1935-1945; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 7)
  - Larry LeSueur's "Normandy, Then and Now," with his first dispatch from Normandy and Introduction, 1935-1945; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 8)
  - Pearl Harbor 50th, WBEZ Chicago: Bob Trout, Larry LeSueur, John M. McDonough, Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 16)
  - Pearl Harbor 50th, Tape II, 1991 December 6; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 9)
  - World News Today, Larry LeSueur Reports on Return from Russia, 1942 November 29; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 10)
  - Interview: Larry LeSueur, John MacVane. KNUS, Denver, 1983 June 5; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 11)
  - LeSueur, Side 3 and 4, 1983 June 5; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 12)
  - Admiral R.E. Byrd, undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 13)
  - World News Today, CBS Morning News: Larry LeSueur, Charles Shaw, 1945 April 15; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 14)
  - Larry LeSueur, Voice of America: Omaha Cemetary, Normandy, 1984 June 5; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 15)
  - Larry LeSueur, Voice of America: Omaha Cemetary, Normandy, 1984 June 6; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 20)
  - CBS Morning News, 1940 September 21-28; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 26)
  - CBS Morning News, 1940 August 22-23; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 17)
  - CBS Morning News, 1940 August 15-20; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 18)
  - CBS Morning News, 1940 July 15-30; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 19)
  - Larry LeSueur, Bob Trout with Nagasaki crew, NPR, 1993 August 6; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 21)
  - CBS News, Tape 1, 1935-1945; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 23)
  - CBS News, Tape 2, 1935-1945; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 22)
  - Press conference November 2, Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 24)
  - Assorted CBS reports, Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 25)
  - London After Dark, 1940 August 24; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 27)
  - John Dunning interview with Larry LeSueur, 1983 January 9; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 28)
    General
    Side 2 is Interview, CBS Morning News, July 11, 1940
  - unlabeled cassettes [5], Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 29)
  - Count Down to Zero, Series 4 (Box 19, Videocassette 1)
  - Finest Hour program 1, Series 4 (Box 19, Videocassette 2)
  - Finest Hour program 2, Series 4 (Box 19, Videocassette 3)
  - Normandy Remembered: 50th Anniversary by Colonel Barney and Vada Oldfield [1 of 2], Series 4; A video commemoration of the 50th anniversary of D-Day and the four Nebraska natives who died in the invasion. Produced by Colonel Barney and Vada Oldfield in association with the Nebraska Normandy Scholarship Fund of the University Nebraska Foundation. 37 minutes (Box 19, Videocassette 4)
  - Normandy Remembered: 50th Anniversary by Colonel Barney and Vada Oldfield [2 of 2], Series 4; A video commemoration of the 50th anniversary of D-Day and the four Nebraska natives who died in the invasion. Produced by Colonel Barney and Vada Oldfield in association with the Nebraska Normandy Scholarship Fund of the University Nebraska Foundation. 37 minutes (Box 19, Videocassette 5)
  - LeSueur interview with Admiral Richard E. Byrd, 1954; Series 4 (Box 19, Reel 1)
  - LeSueur interview with Charles Willis VOA POW, Series 4 (Box 19, Reel 2)
  - unlabeled reel, Series 4 (Box 19, Reel 3)
  - LWF Presents the 3rd Assembly, Series 4 (Reel 1)
  - London After Dark, CBS Transatlantic, 1940 August 24; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 30)
  - London continued, Murrow 6/5/1937 and Thomas, May 1969, 1937-1969; Series 4 (Box 16, Cassette 30)
  - Ed Bliss Tribute, American University, 1999; Series 4 (Box 22, Videocassette 1)
  - unlabeled reel, Series 4 (Box 22, Reel 1)
  - unlabeled reel, Series 4 (Box 22, Reel 2)
  - unlabeled reel, Series 4 (Box 22, Reel 3)
  - unlabeled videocassette, Series 4 (Box 22, Videocassette 2)
- Artifacts, undated; Series 5; 1 Linear Feet
  Artifacts are housed according to size and material.
  This series contains awards and certificates, medallions, badges, key fobs, and other small items used by or given to LeSueur during the course of his broadcast career. Most material is undated but appears to date from the 1960s to 1984.
  - Photographs, Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Bicentennial medallion, Series 5 (Box 17, Item 1)
  - Lyndon Baines Johnson medallion, Series 5 (Box 17, Item 2)
  - hat, Series 5 (Box 17, Item 3)
  - Normandy 40th anniversary badge, 1984; Series 5 (Box 17, Item 4)
  - three key fobs, Series 5 (Box 17, Item 5)
  - leather wallet and case, Series 5 (Box 17, Item 6)
  - business card holder, Series 5 (Box 17, Item 7)
  - foreign currency, Series 5 (Box 17, Item 8)
  - National 4th Infantry Division Association award, 1962; Series 5 (Box 18, Item 1)
  - Awards and certificates, Series 5 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Honorary Tar Heel certificate, 1963; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Oversize photo of LeSueur and Senator Baker, Series 4 (Box 20, Item 1)
  - CBS News promotional book, Series 4 (Box 20, Item 2)
  - Oversize magazines with memorial articles for President Kennedy, Series 4 (Box 20, Item 3)
  - Oversize scrapbook of photos from President Johnson, Series 4 (Box 20, Item 4)
  - American Nobel Anniversary Dinner, 1961; Series 4 (Box 20, Loose-material data_value_missing_9f85c95753332b2d14e7977a4ec23571)
- Clippings, 1940-1988; Series 6; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Arranged by type of clipping.
  This series contains newspaper clippings both by and about LeSueur, as well as clippings about the Battle of Normandy and about President John F. Kennedy. They date from 1940 to 1988. Most of these clippings are photocopies of originals that were compromised by mold and brittle paper.
  - Clippings by LeSueur, 1940-1945; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Clippings by LeSueur, 1940-1945; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Clippings by LeSueur, 1940-1945; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Clippings by LeSueur, 1940-1945; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Clippings by LeSuer - "10 Questions about Stalin", 15 March 1943; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Clippings about LeSueur, 1942-1984; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Clippings about Normandy, 1984-1988; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "Last Rites for a President," Washington Post, 1963; Series 6 (Box 15, Folder 7)